# Carlos Felipe Alcala Perez

#### DATA SCIENTIST

Milwaukee, WI.

□ (+1) 414-426-6814 | Salcala21@gmail.com | Dalcala21 | Dalcala21 | Carlos F. Alcala

# **Summary**

Current Site Reliability Engineer at start-up company Kasa. 7+ years experience specializing in the backend development, infrastructure automation, and computer hacking/security. Super nerd who loves Vim, Linux and OS X and enjoys to customize all of the development environment. Interested in devising a better problem-solving method for challenging tasks, and learning new technologies and tools if the need arises.

# Skills.

Programming R, Python, Matlab, VBA, RMarkdown, ŁTEX

Applications Sublime Text, Git, Github, Visual Studio Code

**Languages** English, Spanish (native)

# Work Experience \_

Johnson Controls Oct. 2011 - Jan. 2020

PRINCIPAL RESEARCH ENGINEER Milwaukee, WI Dec. 2017 - Jan. 2018

- I used advanced optimization and data analytics methods to improve the efficiency of heating, ventilation and air conditioning (HVAC) systems.
- I was involved in the transfer of newly developed technology into products and applications.

SENIOR RESEARCH ENGINEER Milwaukee, WI May 2015 - Dec. 2017

I developed methods for monitoring the performance of PID controllers, to detect steady state operation of HVAC equipment, and reduce energy
consumption in wireless thermostats while keeping acceptable comfort standards. I used advanced mathematical tools to develop these methods,
as well as artificial intelligence, machine learning and traditional statistical methods.

SENIOR RESEARCH ENGINEER Mexico City, Mexico Jan. 2013 - May 2015

• I developed data-driven methods for fault detection and diagnosis in connected chillers.

SENIOR RESEARCH ENGINEER Milwaukee, WI Oct. 2011 - Jan. 2013

- I developed a method for adaptive sampling of PID controllers.

**The Dow Chemical Company**Freeport, TX
May 2010 - Aug. 2010

SUMMER RESEARCH INTERN

· I developed an Excel application for multivariate statistical monitoring of continuous and batch processes.

Capstone Technology Seattle, WA 2006 - 2009

SUMMER ENGINEERING INTERN May. 2009 - Aug. 2009

• I developed a multivariate image analysis application to monitor combustion efficiency in furnaces.

SUMMER ENGINEERING INTERN May. 2007 - Aug. 2007

• I developed a multivariate statistical application for statistical modeling and prediction in chemical processes.

SUMMER ENGINEERING INTERN May. 2006 - Aug. 2006

• I developed a multivariate statistical application for detection and diagnosis of sensor and process faults.

NMC North Microelectronics Beijing, China Jun. 2008 - Jul. 2008

SUMMER ENGINEERING INTERN

• I developed a multivariate statistical application for monitoring the operation of a semiconductor manufacturing process.

# **Education**

#### **University of Southern California**

Los Angeles, CA

Aug. 2007 - Aug. 2011

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN CHEMICAL ENGINEERING

• I was awarded a Roberto Rocca Fellowship to do my PhD studies.

#### The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

Aug. 2005 - May 2007

MASTER OF SCIENCE IN CHEMICAL ENGINEERING

• I was awarded a Fulbright scholarship to do my Masters degree.

#### Instituto Tecnologico de Ciudad Madero

Ciudad Madero, Mexico

Aug. 1999 - Dec 2003

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN CHEMICAL ENGINEERING

· Graduated Summa Cum Laude.

# **Certifications**

Statistics with R Duke University

Coursera

OCT. 29, 2018

Credential ID: UWG3PS5EXMBJ

 Machine Learning
 University of Washington
 Coursera

FEB. 1, 2017

Credential ID: 2VHFDHW5GUK6

 Data Science
 Johns Hopkins University
 Coursera

APR. 20, 2016

Credential ID: W9DB45S3CGDZ

# **Publications**

#### **Patents**

Control system with response time estimation and automatic operating parameter adjustment Carlos F. Alcala Perez, Timothy I. Salsbury

US Patent 10324424, 2019

Control system with asynchronous wireless data transmission

Carlos F. Alcala Perez, Kirk H. Drees

US Patent 10333810, 2019

Building climate control system with decoupler for independent control of interacting feedback loops

Timothy I. Salsbury, Carlos F. Alcala Perez, John M. House, Christopher R. Amundson *US Patent 10253997*, 2019

Building management system with voting-based fault detection and diagnostics

Carlos F. Alcala Perez

US Patent 10401262, 2019

Control system with response time estimation

Carlos F. Alcala Perez, Timothy I. Salsbury

US Patent 10317856, 2019

Feedback control system with normalized performance indices for setpoint alarming

Timothy I. Salsbury, Carlos F. Alcala Perez, Michael J. Ajax

US Patent 10197977, 2019

System and method for output compensation in flow sensors using pulse width modulation

Carlos F. Alcala Perez, Kirk H Drees, Timothy I Salsbury

US Patent App. 15/908,041, 2018

System and method for output compensation in flow sensors

Carlos F. Alcala Perez, Kirk H Drees

US Patent App. 15/897,987, 2018

Normalized indices for feedback control loops

Timothy I. Salsbury, Carlos F. Alcala Perez

US Patent 9920943, 2018

Thermostat with efficient wireless data transmission

Timothy I Salsbury, Carlos F. Alcala Perez, Homero L Noboa

US Patent App. 15/618,492, 2017

Building control system with decoupler for independent control of interacting feedback loops

Timothy I Salsbury, Carlos F. Alcala Perez, John M House, Christopher R Amundson

US Patent App. 16/253,965, 2017

Systems and methods for steady state detection

Carlos F. Alcala Perez

US Patent App. 15/449,732, 2017

Systems and methods for automatically creating and using adaptive pca models to control building equipment

Carlos F. Alcala Perez

US Patent App. 15/279,336, 2016

Systems and methods for adaptive sampling rate adjustment

Carlos F. Alcala Perez, Timothy I. Salsbury

US Patent 9395708, 2016

Building management system with predictive diagnostics

Carlos F. Alcala Perez, Samuel F. Hamilton

US Patent App. 15/188,824, 2016

#### **Journal Papers**

A method for setpoint alarming using a normalized index

Carlos F. Alcala, Timothy I. Salsbury

Control Engineering Practice 60.3 (2017) pp. 1-6. 2017

An extremum-seeking control method driven by input-output correlation

Timothy I Salsbury, John M House, Carlos F Alcala, Yaoyu Li

Journal of Process Control 58 (2017) pp. 106–116. Elsevier, 2017

Analysis and generalization of fault diagnosis methods for process monitoring

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Journal of Process Control 21.3 (2011) pp. 322-330. 2011

Generalized reconstruction-based contributions for output-relevant fault diagnosis with application to the tennessee eastman process

Gang Li, Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin, Donghua Zhou

Control Systems Technology, IEEE Transactions on 19.5 (Sept. 2011) pp. 1114–1127. 2011

Reconstruction-based contribution for process monitoring with kernel principal component analysis

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Industrial & Engineering Chemistry Research 49.17 (2010) pp. 7849-7857. 2010

Reconstruction-based contribution for process monitoring

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Automatica 45.7 (2009) pp. 1593-1600. 2009

# **Conference Papers**

Self-optimizing Control of an Air Source Heat Pump

Zhongfan Zhao, Yaoyu Li, Timothy I Salsbury, Carlos F Alcala, John M House

2019 American Control Conference (ACC), 2019

#### Identification of a Self-Optimizing Control Structure from Normal Operating Data

Carlos F Alcala, Timothy I Salsbury, John M House

2019 American Control Conference (ACC), 2019

# Decoupling Method for PI Controllers via Setpoint Modification Applied to HVAC Systems

Timothy I Salsbury, John M House, Carlos F Alcala

ASME 2018 Dynamic Systems and Control Conference, 2018

# Reduction of Transmissions in Wireless Thermostats with Send-on-Delta Sampling and a Deadband Filter Carlos F Alcala, Timothy I Salsbury

2018 Annual American Control Conference (ACC), 2018

### Decoupling Method for PI Controllers via Setpoint Modification Applied to HVAC Systems

Timothy I. Salsbury, John M. House, Carlos F. Alcala

Proceedings of the Dynamic Systems and Control Conference, 2018

# Reduction of Transmissions in Wireless Thermostats with Send-on-Delta Sampling and a Deadband Filter

C. F. Alcala, T. I. Salsbury

Proceedings of the 2018 Annual American Control Conference (ACC), 2018

#### Model Selection for Predicting the Return Time from Night Setback

John E Seem, John M House, Carlos F Alcala

Proceedings of the International High Performance Buildings Conference, 2016

# Two new normalized EWMA-based indices for control loop performance assessment

Timothy I. Salsbury, Carlos F. Alcala

Proceedings of the American Control Conference (ACC), 2015

#### Monitoring of dynamic processes with subspace identification and principal component analysis

Ricardo Dunia Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Proceedings of the 8th IFAC International Symposium on Fault Detection, Supervision and Safety of Technical Processes, 2012, Mexico City, Mexico

#### Unified analysis of diagnosis methods for process monitoring

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Oin

Proceedings of the 7th IFAC International Symposium on Fault Detection, Supervision and Safety of Technical Processes, 2009, Barcelona, Spain

# Unification of contribution analysis for process monitoring

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Proceedings of the 2008 AIChE Annual Meeting, 2008, Philadelphia, USA

#### Reconstruction-based contribution for process monitoring

Carlos Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Proceedings of the 17th IFAC World Congress, 2008, Seoul, Korea